# 去年老王家的杮子哦 今年又長了 一樹都是
Remember Wang’s persimmon trees last year? They’re growing well again this year. The persimmons are all over the trees.
# 我用那望遠看了一下 好多啊
There are a lot. I just saw them with a telescope.
# 上次在這裡摔了一跤
Last time I fell here.
# 這次不能摔跤了
No more this time.
# 啊這裡 有水 麻煩了
Ah! Here, here’s water. That’s not good.
# 幸好我有刀
I have a knife with me, fortunately.
# 逢山開路 遇水架橋 哪有上不去的
Though the mountains are high and the oceans are wide, I can always create my path.
# 哎呀 甘蔗哦
Aya! Sugarcanes!
# 你看 他種的這個
Look! He planted them,
# 他種的這個甘蔗
he planted these sugarcanes.
# 這種甘蔗很好吃的哦 但是在太嫩了
This kind of sugarcane is really tasty. But they’re too young now.
# 它沒有 它 不能吃那麼快
They don’t, they, not so soon,
# 到要天的時候就有的吃啦
not until winter, before they can be eaten.
# 你看 這兩根是我的 這一根是他的
Look! These two are mine, and this one is his.
# 挨在一起種的
We planted them side by side.
# 路都沒有啦
I can’t even see the path.
# 這路也太難走啦
What a difficult path.
# 上去看一下有沒有
I'm gonna go up there and see if there are any.
# 你看這樹 還是那麼大
Have a look at this tree. It’s still that big.
# 不好上哦
Not easy to climb
# 啊 終於看到幾個了
Ah! Finally, I can see some of them now.
# 這個快黃啦
They'll be ripe very soon.
# 黃的哦
This one is ripe.
# 這兩個杮子 這個可以吃的哦這個 這個直接可以咬的
These two persimmons… This can be eaten now, this one. I can bite it right away.
# 啊~好澀啊
Ah~ It’s so acerbic!
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 本來這個不是脆杮子嗎 怎麼那麼澀
Isn't it a crunchy persimmon! Where comes the acerbic taste?
# 啊 受不了啦
Ah! I can’t stand it!
# 把它摘 把它全部摘回去吧 摘回去
Let me pick, pick them all back home, pick them back home.
# 那個甚麼 ou一下就可以啦
How do you say it? Ripen it, ripen it for a while. Then it will be fine.
# 它自己會熟的
They will become ripe by themselves.
# 應該這個皮澀 它裡面肉應該不澀
I think the acerbic taste comes from the peel, not from the pulp inside.
# 嗯 好像是誒
Um! Seems to be
# 這脆杮子
This crunchy persimmon…
# 怪不得
No wonder
# 皮不點澀
The peel is a bit acerbic.
# 你看 很脆吧
Look! It’s really crunchy, isn’t it?
# 我全部把它摘回去ou一下
Let me pick them all and ripen them at home.
# ou一下更好吃
They would taste much better.
# 我全部集中起來 摘到來
I’m gonna put them all together, pick them all,
# 放家裡 放幾天那就可以吃啦
leave them at home, store them for a few days and we can start eating.
# 就一個
Just one.
# 這裡好幾個大的
Here are a couple of big ones.
# 你看這種脆杮子 手摔就爆掉的哦 這個
Look! This kind of crunchy persimmons, simply crack when they drop, this one.
# 家 在家裡幾天就可以吃啦 很好吃的
At home, store them at home for a few days. Then they can be eaten. It’s really tasty.
# 哇 搞得蠻多的
Wa! We have quite a lot here.
# 可以啦
It’s alright now.
# 把它的樹 樹上的都 幾乎全部摘完啦
We’ve almost taken, taken everything, everything in the tree.
# 反正老王不要了
No worries. Wang doesn’t want them anymore.
# 夠吃啦
It’s enough now.
# 把它帶回去
Let me take them back.
# 袋子也沒一個 完啦
Gosh! I don’t even have a bag.
# 這個 這個杮子 好多杮子就直接這樣背回去算啦
These, these persimmons, many of them can simply be carried on the back right away.
# 回去等一下 把這個是杮子汁搞到這衣服下
Well, um… what if the juice stains on the T-shirt?
# 怕老婆罵
My wife will scold me.
# 所以挑一下
So I gotta choose,
# 把好的背回去
and take only the good ones.
# 壞的 叫攝影小哥拿
The rotten ones, I’ll ask Mr. Cameraman to take them.
# 你看 好多的 好多都是好的
Look! Many, many of them are good.
# 你看 這樣可以吧 這等一下攝影小哥會撿
Look! It should be fine, right? Mr. Cameraman will pick the rest in a while.
# 我先走啦
I’m leaving first.
# 路過老刻家的那個黃豆 他家的黃豆都熟啦
We pass by Liu’s, Liu’s soy beans. His beans are already ripe.
# 我再不吃掉的話等下就被那個老鼠吃掉
They would be eaten by the rats if I don’t eat them now.
# 為了不讓老鼠吃掉 我來幫他消滅
In order to safe them from the rats, I shall help him take care of them.
# 你看 草都不割
Look! He just lets the weeds grow.
# 可以哦 這些黃豆
It’s not bad, these beans.
# 都是很漂亮的哦
All are very pretty, you know.
# 要把這個葉子要摘掉 不摘掉這葉子就不好看
These leaves need to be picked away. Otherwise it doesn’t look good.
# 看到沒有 這就是粒粒飽滿
See? Every bean is round and fat.
# 又多
And there are a lot.
# 等拿回去煮一下 特別好吃的這個 放點鹽
Let me take them back and cook them. It’s exceptionally tasty, with some salt.
# 放點鹽煮一下
Cook them with some salt.
# 味道杠杠滴 你看
Delizioso! Look!
# 就這一串一串的往下煮
I just put them into the pot in bunches.
# 再多搞點 太少了
Let me take more. Too few here.
# 哎呀 割這個最好割了
Aya! Cutting this is always a pleasure.
# 一刀一個
Down the knife, off the beans
# 不用留情
No mercy
# 一刀就把它割下來
No extra effort needed.
# 好 夠啦
Alright! Enough!
# 把這葉子摘下來
Let me pick away the leaves.
# 你看 把這個黃豆
Look! The beans,
# 這樣 直直把它擺好一點
here, I leave them straight and tidy.
# 煮的才香
So that it smells good.
# 也沒多少啊這裡 我以為很多嘞
There aren’t really too many. I thought there are lot.
# 一搞 搞出來就那麼一點點
But it, but it turns out to be just a tiny little bit.
# 這樣就可以啦
So everything is alright now.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt
# 這個鹽要稍微加多一點 沒事
No worries. It really needs slightly more salt.
# 好啦 就這樣 蓋上鍋蓋 直接煮就可以啦
Alright! That's it! Cover the lid, and I can start cooking right away.
# 好啦 半個小時 夠啦
Alright! Half an hour. It would be enough.
# 應該差不多啦
It should be done now.
# 哎呀 嗯 好香
Aya! Um! It smells so good!
# 搞一串吃一下
Let me take a bunch and have a try.
# 你看這個 這個豆子
Have a look at these, these beans.
# 嗯 很香
Um! It smells really good.
# 你看 就這樣的豆子
Look! These are the beans.
# 太好吃啦
Simply delicious
# 吃的時候要從頭到尾
It should always be eaten all the way down from the top,
# 或者從尾吃到頭
or all the way up from the bottom.
# 這樣就不會錯過每一個 每一粒豆子了
Then no one, no beans would be left out.
# 要是你亂吃的話到時候
But if you just eat randomly,
# 吃到哪裡你都不知道
you never know which one you have eaten.
# 誒 掉了一個
Ey? I dropped one.
# 你看 這樣
Look! I’m showing you.
# 一截一截吃過去
Eat from here, part by part.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我要煮飯啦
I gotta cook now.
# 天氣那麼晚
It’s so late now.
# 早點吃飽 早點睡覺
Early meal means early sleep.